Guide to the Edwin Peacock Papers, 1915-1997 and undated, bulk 1940s-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edwin Peacock papers 1915-1997 and undated, bulk 1940s-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Peacock, Edwin Davis, 1910-1989.
0.8 linear feet Extent: 630 Items
Co-owner (with John Zeigler) of the Book Basement in Charleston, S.C. Letters (some copies) to Edwin Peacock and John Zeigler, chiefly regarding their friend, author Carson McCullers. Many letters are from translators and biographers of McCullers (Virginia Carr, Jacques Tournier, and Robert Duparc). Includes letters from both Carson and Reeves McCullers to Peacock and Zeigler as well as copies of the McCullers letters to each other while Reeves served in the armed forces in France during World War II. Some letters were written by Carson McCullers to Peacock during her stays at Yaddo. Contains playbills of McCullers' plays, reviews of her books and plays, and other printed material concerning her as well as 56 photographs of the McCullers, their family, and their friends.
RL.01005
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edwin Peacock Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1989, 1991, and 1998.
Biographical Note
Born in 1910; died in 1989. A bookstore owner in Charleston, S.C., and a childhood friend of Carson McCullers. Introduced her to a number of other writers, including Reeves McCullers. Throughout his life, he provided the author with spiritual guidance and support for her writing.
Collection Overview
The Edwin Peacock Papers span the dates 1915 to 1997, with the majority of the items dating from the 1940s to 1997, and provide many insights into the life and work of Carson McCullers through materials in three series: Correspondence, Photographs, and Printed Materials. The Correspondence Series, largest in the collection, is comprised primarily of letters to Edwin Peacock and John Zeigler. Many are from translators and biographers of McCullers (Virginia Carr, Jacques Tournier, and Robert Duparc). There is also significant correspondence by the author's husband, Reeves McCullers, and copies of letters to each other while Reeves served in the armed forces in France during World War II.
The bulk of the Photographs Series consists of black and white snapshots primarily from the 1940s and 1950s. The majority of them represent Carson McCullers, her friends and family, including Edwin Peacock, John Zeigler, Mary Mercer, her sister, and her mother.
The Printed Materials and Clippings Series consists of documents related to the work of Carson McCullers. Formats include playbills, critical articles, reviews, and clippings. There is also a high-school essay on McCullers by the niece of John Zeigler, and materials related to various conferences and symposiums about the author.
Subject Headings
Peacock, Edwin Davis, 1910-1989; Carr, Virginia Spencer; McCullers, Carson, 1917-1967; Tournier, Jacques; Duparc, Robert Fouques; McCullers, Reeves, 1913-1953; Women authors, American -- Georgia; Women authors -- Relations with men; Authors, American -- Correspondence; Yaddo (Artist's colony); Clippings; Photographs
Related Material
Related materials include the Carson McCullers Papers, the Virginia Spencer Carr Papers, the Mary E. Mercer Collection of Carson McCullers-Mary Tucker Correspondence, and the Mary Sames Tucker Papers, all housed at Duke University's David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Duke also houses the papers of John Zeigler, Peacock's friend and bookstore co-owner.
In addition, the Edwin Peacock Papers previously contained letters from Dawn Langley Simmons, who was a friend of Peacock and Zeigler, as well as photographs and printed materials relating to Simmons and McCullers. At the request of both donors, the Simmons material was transferred to the Dawn Pepita Langley Hall Simmons Papers held by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke University. Please see the note below, at Box 2.
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1943-1997 and undated, (2 boxes)
  The bulk of the series consists of correspondence written to the bookstore owners Edwin Peacock and John Zeigler, although there are a few letters addressed to Zeigler's neighbor, Robert Holmes. Prominent correspondents are Carson McCullers and her husband Reeves, who wrote to each other nearly every day while Reeves served in the army during World War II. There is also significant correspondence from the biographers of McCullers, especially Virginia Carr, as well as Jacques Tournier and Robert Duparc. Other correspondence includes letters McCullers wrote to Peacock during her stay at Yadoo, letters from Reeves's friend, John Vincent Adams, and letters from the sister of McCullers, Margarita Smith. Topics relate primarily to McCullers's work and to personal matters. Folders in the series are arranged alphabetically; items within folders are in chronological order.
  - Adams, John Vincent, 1967 Oct. 31-1976 Feb. 11 (Box 1)
  - Carr, Virginia (Box 1)
    - 1970 July 9-1972 Dec. 21 (Box 1)
    - 1973 Feb. 9-1977 Sept. 10 and undated (Box 1)
    - 1978 Feb. 22-1989 June 8 (Box 1)
  - McCullers, Carson, 1943-1963 and undated (Box 1)
  - McCullers, Carson and Reeves (Box 1)
    - 1943 Feb. 23-Dec. 5 (Box 1)
    - 1944 Feb. 19-Sept. 17 (Box 1)
    - 1944 Oct. 5-Dec. 28 and undated (Box 1)
    - 1945 Jan. 1-Nov. 25 (Box 1)
    - 1951 Aug. 7-Sept. 23 and undated (Box 1)
  - McCullers, Reeves, 1944 Dec. 3-1953 Feb. 15 (Box 2)
  - Rich, Nancy B., 1976 Oct. 8-1987 June 25 (Box 2)
  - Simmons, Dawn Hall (Box 2)
    The correspondence and photographs of Dawn Pepita Langley Hall Simmons and the newspaper clippings and magazine articles about her from the Edwin Peacock Papers have been transferred to the Dawn Pepita Langley Hall Simmons Papers at the request of both donors. See the reference archivist on duty regarding the restrictions of the Simmons Papers. (Transferred materials are housed in Simmons Papers Oversized Box 4 and with a Simmons addition.)
  - Smith, Margarita, 1945 May 1-1978 Jan. 9 (Box 2)
  - Tournier, Jacques and Duparc, Robert, 1976 Sept. 4-1979 Dec. 25 and undated (Box 2)
  - Other correspondents, 1940 July 30-1997 Feb. 17 and undated (Box 2)
- Photographs Series, 1915-1963 and undated, bulk 1940s-1963, (1 box) (Box 2)
  Contains 62 photographs (7 color, 55 black and white), one negative and two postcards. Several photographs come from the mid-1930s, but the bulk is from the late 1940s, after Reeves returned from the war, and from the McCullers' stay in Bachivillers, France during the early 1950s. There are also some snapshots from the 1960s. Apart from McCullers herself, the people represented are primarily family members (her mother and sister) and friends, including Mary Mercer, Edwin Peacock, John Zeigler, and the Italian writer Alberto Moravia. The series is arranged in roughly chronological order, accompanied by a partial itemized inventory.
  - 1915-1963 and undated (Box 2)
- Printed Materials and Clippings Series, 1950-1997 and undated, (1 box) (Box 2)
  The materials in this series relate primarily to the work of Carson McCullers, and include playbills, critical articles, and reviews of her books and plays. Particularly well documented is The Member of the Wedding. There are also a few ephemeral items, including newspaper clippings, obituaries, a high-school essay on McCullers written by John Zeigler's niece, and information about various conferences and symposiums about the writer. Folders are arranged alphabetically; items within are arranged in chronological order.
  - Articles, programs, and playbills, 1950-1996 and undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
    - 1940 June 8 - 1954 Feb. 26 and undated (Box 2)
    - 1960-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1997 and undated (Box 2)
  - High-school essay on McCullers, 1991 April (Box 2)